what are the side effects um not too
much you know if you feel like suicidal
or something just give me a
call welcome back to the trt and hormone
optimization YouTube channel and we have
a new guest today Nik Misa welcome niik
thank you Stephen it's a pleasure to be
here nice to have you so maybe let's
start by introducing yourself absolutely
uh so again my name is D MLA uh I am a
family nurse practitioner by trade I
live in Cincinnati Ohio over here in the
United States um and I've got a couple
different roles I'm a I'm a clinic owner
uh so I own Apollo Health optimization
uh where we treat men and women for
hormone replacement therapy uh and then
I also uh own and operate a a new uh
education platform called HRT University
um which is really exciting uh we
actually are going to be launching I
don't know when this will air but uh
we'll be launching that course
officially at the end of April of this
year um again training providers uh from
all walks of life nurse practitioners
Physicians whoever they may be uh in
doing hormone replacement therapy uh so
we're looking at it as like the a really
comprehensive uh product uh again both
from the male and female side of things
talking even about thyroid and some of
the adjunct hormones oxytocin melatonin
things like that uh so so we're really
excited about that and and again perfect
timing I appreciate you have me on so I
could even even discuss some of that
stuff too right awesome so you were
introduced to me by uh our mutual friend
uh just J in gr um yeah he said you're
well versed in all kinds of functional
medicine as well in combination with the
trt HRT so maybe let's start uh with
mental health because I have a lot of
patients myself who are young men who
are on anti-depressants and I often
wonder if it wouldn't be better to get
them on trt so probably yeah you you
experience the same thing absolutely um
and by the way your channel I I think is
just so fantastic it's such a good
Outlet so many of my patients in the
United States have have seen your
channel have have come to me just via
your channel um I I joke and say it's
it's a it's a gateway drug for a lot of
my patients in the in the best way
possible so it's been really I'm
thankful for you you know I I started uh
initially in the functional medicine
World um you know it was probably almost
10 years ago now uh and training even
before that I I knew right away that I
was never going to get into conventional
medicine so to speak uh my my
grandfather's a retired physician a
wonderful guy he gave up his license
four years ago at 90 years old uh he's
he's just a student of medicine and is a
constant learner uh but he he told me
you know ni could never go into medicine
you'll hate it it's miserable you know
he was kind of during at least in the
United States during the era of
insurance moving in uh oxy you know
oxycodone and all the all the
prescription pain pill clinics are on
the Rise um so I think unfortunately he
had a very negative uh last you know
decade or so in medicine but um you know
I said I love this stuff and I just I
know there's a better way to do it um so
I started seeking out a lot of you know
Physicians nurse practitioners whoever
uh these people were in my local
community doing some of the holistic and
Integrative Medicine um and they were
amazing they were some some some of the
best people I ever met uh doing some
really wild stuff I mean you know so
this is back in like the you know maybe
like 2010 2011 era we're you know I'm
looking at people in H baric oxygen
Chambers and things of that nature uh
and I just remember thinking this is so
cool this is like a science fiction
movie in real life and and watching
patients really get amazing results um
you know so so again we I'm looking at
this guy in hyperbaric chamber for PTSD
and and concussion uh and thinking oh my
God like I I've never even heard of
these two first of all being a
combination of a problem and let alone
something like this being a therapy so
it immediately got me interested in just
that that that side of medicine um going
into this cash-based system kind of
going against the whole big Insurance
stuff um and and I knew right away that
I really wanted to explore mental health
a little bit more um and I know you know
this Steph so I'm probably preaching the
choir but I think in medicine in general
at large uh Psychiatry if I can I'm not
trying to disparage them as as a as a
group but it's it's one of the few areas
of medicine where I think truly there's
just practically zero objective data and
values driving it uh you know it's it's
it's all mostly subjective uh you know
maybe we have a phq9 or or some sort of
you know formula where we're concocting
that you have major depression symptoms
but at the end of the day we can't slice
your brain open and see it it's not a
real strict pathology right um and so I
thought you know this is so
unacceptable BEC because if if this was
ever something that would happen in card
iology first of all no patient would
take that doctor seriously and no other
medical provider would take that doctor
seriously and and maybe to some degree
that's some of the some of the
stereotypes around Psychiatry but I
thought there there are objective things
we can do in Psychiatry um there's a
fantastic um again I won't try to get
too nerdy here uh her name is Dr Joanna
monrie um she's out of she might be in
Oxford University maybe I know I know
she's uh in England um amazing PhD MD
who's done fantastic amounts of research
around depression and ssris um and in
2022 she put out a met analyses more or
less describing that
serotonin as a as a
neurotransmitter there's really no
evidence whatsoever that it has anything
to do with major
depression um which of course
everybody's like what well we what are
we going to do with that um you know
we're not going to stop prescribing
zolof and paxel and all these major
drugs so um but again it just kind of
spoke more and more to this idea that
you know depression in general anxiety
even things like bipolar disorder and
schizophrenia there there's no real hard
science behind it in terms of the
pathology what we do know is that it
appears a lot of these tend to be a
culmination of problems uh right so so
uh you know think about uh you're not
eating well you're not sleeping well uh
maybe you have low testosterone maybe
you have some sort of primary
hypogonadism or verical that's affecting
you and and this is unknown um but there
are objective things that we can do to
attempt to try to discover some of those
things so you know I I've I've spoken
you know nationally now which I'm I'm
really excited to be able to do this at
at different conferences and stuff um
about how you know if you're I don't
care who you are if you're a primary
care provider or if you're or if you're
in Psych itself we should be doing these
objective measures in tandem with
obviously subjective measures as well
just like we would in any other area of
medicine before we even consider moving
into the world of psychotropics um and
and that I think maybe more
controversial St but I don't even know
if much of the psychotropics are
necessary and I think they produce more
harm than good especially in the long
run yeah um
so um do patients with depression
consult you maybe they want to come off
of their
ssris what do you do do you a hormonal
examination yeah yeah so I I always told
uh my patients you know I'm not a psych
provider uh or practitioner by trade um
if your depression happens to get better
by what we're doing fantastic uh so I
really became known for for helping
people suffering from major depression
uh perhaps they were told that they
should attempt uh to utilize an SSRI or
an anti-depressant of some sort and
maybe they felt uncomfortable about that
there was something about it that just
seemed fishy uh maybe they've been on it
for 10 years and you know they're
they're liido is terrible their erectile
dysfunction is unbelievable and they're
you know certainly not feeling all that
much better these patients would come to
me um and and I would either I would
educate them how I think hey maybe we
should look at your testosterone and
your thyroid numbers and all kinds of
different things before we jump to that
um if they were on an SSI I would
educate them on on you know again
Stephen I'm not here to disparage
psychotropics necessarily but um most
patients aren't getting inform form Med
consent around those medications I mean
and and I get it a lot of patients are
coming to these Physicians nurse
practitioners whomever in a really bad
place uh and they're being told hey this
is this will work take the Zoloft uh
you'll feel fantastic was it what are
the side effects H not too much you know
if you feel like suicidal or
somethingone just give me a call that is
scary but there are many more things
besides just suicidal ideation there's
again metabolic syndrome uh risk
increase uh uh which obviously includes
a weight gain increase for a lot of
patients decrease beo um the six major
uh anti-depressants or ssris in the
modern healthcare industry right now all
of them at least in in Vivo it appears
uh decrease sex hormone steroidogenesis
or the production of sex hormones um so
so it's no wonder that a lot of people
also are suffering from the LOL laido
and stuff but at the at the very least I
think it's important that those patients
be given that amount of informed consent
so at least when they come see me I tell
them uh I'm not I'm not here to say that
that that potentially they can't improve
some symptoms but symptom Improvement
can be done in a variety of different
ways yeah um yeah anyway sorry yes so
you explained to them that uh they might
be low in testosterone and if you get
them on trt they might be able to get of
their anti-depressants that's it um you
know and again it's it's a obviously
depression is multifactorial um you know
if you're in a bad relationship with
your wife or your husband it doesn't
mean that testosterone's magically going
to fix that or or anything's going to
magically fix that but I think at the
very least and I think you've seen this
Stephen with many of your patients
giving people testosterone um I I always
term it this way and going back to masau
like hierarchy of needs I I think
hormones are are the like one of the
most foundational things leading to
self-actualization at the top of that
pyramid right you need to be able to eat
and breathe and have a roof over your
head and I I think hormones go even
below so almost below breathing um I I
mean because without them it is very
difficult to to be that best version of
yourself um and it's clear I mean we we
see that in animal models we see that in
human uh studies and things of that
nature so I I I always educate around
look we're going to start testosterone
we as as you continue to improve meaning
oh you know ni my libido's a little bit
better and I I'm waking up and I'm going
for walks or maybe I'm working out then
we can start having a conversation
around slowly but surely weaning off of
that anti-depressant or SSRI and and
again getting into a much better
position so that when we actually come
off of it you're also not you know
relapsing essentially